	# MAKE NOTICE THAT THE PATHS ARE SPECIFIED BASED ON POWERSHELL'S NOMENCLATURE

#### PREVIOUS CHAPTERS' NOTES ####

	--> Name of the branch where HEAD pointer is currently located (refs\heads\<branch name>)
			
			> cat .\.git\HEAD


	--> Commit's SHA-1 hexadecimal 40-digit identifier number the HEAD is pointing at right now
			
			> cat .\.git\refs\heads\<branch name>


	--> Add new remote repository.
			
			> git remote [add <name of the remote> <url>]


	--> Show information about a given repository.
			
			> git remote [show <name of the remote>] 


	--> If we want to take files from working area directly to the commit state, hence skipping staging phase, we can use the following command:
			
			>git commit -am <commit message>
					
			*ALL untracked changes will be added to the commit when using the above command.
			*Note that only modifications are going to be add to the commit. New or deleted files cannot be commited this way.

	--> A good practice when working in projects is to make commits where the changes made are conceptually related within each commit. An example could be that changes
			into the blog section of a webpage should not be related with changes made to the user profile section.
			
			* Commit messages can have prefixed signatures at the beginnig, helping us identifying what the commit is related with:
					"[js,css] add class to the Stats component" 

			* Commit messages should not exceed 72 characters long.

### CHAPTER 05 - Making Changes to Files ###

	*** Viewing log of commits already made ***

		git log [--oneline] [--since=2020-02-01] [--until=2020-02-08] 
		git log [--author="Oscar"] [--grep (get-regExp)="Init"] [-n num (Will retrieve as many commits as "num" we specify, starting from the most recent)]

	*** Vieweing changes with diff ***
			
		->Git diff shows changes between the local repo and the working directory/area/tree. The --staged flag checks changes in staged files.
					
				git diff [<fileName>] [--text] [--staged]

	*** Deleting a file ***
			
		->This command will remove the file permanently. We can then make a new commit with the deletion of the file
					
				git rm <file name> 

		->An alternate approach would be to remove the file manually (which would move the file to the trash can) and the execute the git rm command as before.

	*** Moving a file ***

		->This command will rename/move a file from provided source and destination. A new commit with this change should be make next.
					
				git mv <sourcePath> <destinationPath>

		->Another approach would be to rename/move files manually, which will be taken bit Git as a delete-then-create like operation (separately).
			We would then have to add the git new file operation and remove (using rm) the git remove operation. 
			This approach is commonly suggested when dealing with a several amount of moving/renaming operations at once instead of just a couple of them.

### CHAPTER 07 - Undoing Changes ####

	*** Undoing working directory changes ***

		->When changes need to be undone to files in the working directory, we can checkout those files from the last commit made in the branch where they were added:
					
			git checkout -- <file name> 

				* The double dash -- is used to tell git that we are referring to a file and not a different branch. In other words, we want to 
					checkout the given file in the current branch.
				* The previous command will remove all changes made to the given file in the working directory, restoring the version from the last commit in the branch.

	*** Unstaging files ***
			
		->The command in this case differs entirely from the one used when undoing working tree changes:

				git reset HEAD <file name>

				* This is basically saying Git to look the HEAD pointer (it points to the last commit of the current branch). Conceptually similar to what git checkout -- does.

	*** Amending commmits ***

		->Due to the way that Git keeps track of changes and relations (parent-child relationships) between commits, we should not make direct changes to commits other than the
			ones a the tip of any given branch (last commits). Git generates a SHA-1 key for every commit we make; this hashed 40-digit hexadecimal key represents the information 
			from the commit related to its author, creation date, message content and the parent (previous) commit. The latter implies that every commit has a reference to the one 
			immediately before it. 
			Git generates a new hashed SHA-1 with any change to the data mentioned before. A new generated hashed key for an older commit would break all the relations Git relays 
			upon to keep track of our files change after that modified commit.

		->Knowing the importance of keeping older commits unchanged, we can proceed to only modify the last commit in any given branch we desired, in cases where we want to modify
			the commit message or add/modify/remove files to the commit for example. We can use the following command, after for that:

				git commit -amend -m <commit message>

	*** Retrieving Old Versions ***

		->In order to keep Git's data integrity across commits, when a change from a previous commit needs to be undone, the correct way of achieving it is
			by retrieving an old version of the changes we desire to undo and based on them make a new commit.

				* It is good practice to refer to the old commit's SHA-1 key number when commiting the changes.

				git checkout <commit> -- <fileName>

					* After running this command, the file retrieved from a particular commit will be placed directly into the staging index.

	*** Reverting a Commit ***
					
		->The following command is helpful when we need to revert changes from the previous commit. Anything added will be deleted, anything deleted will be added back again
			and any modification made is going to be undone, taking the file to its previous unchanges state.

				git revert <commit>

					* The default text editor from git config options will be opened to ask us for a message for the revert commit.
						It will have a default message that we can retain in case no additional or custom information is needed.
					* The revert command automatically makes a new commit based on the one we reverted. This approach works really
						well when the changes are simple (going from state B to state A).

*** Using 'reset' to undo commits ***

	->Allow us to specify where the HEAD pointer should point to. Think of it in terms of the metafor of a tape recording system, where 
		when we rewind the tape to some point and start recording again, all the data recorded past the point to which we rewinded will be lost.

	->Git reset has 3 possible options we can define to control its behavior:

		*	--soft is going to move HEAD pointer to the specified commit without changing staging index or working directory.
			It represents the safest of all options from the reset command. The only thing that will change is the repository
			directory, which is going to have the state of the commit we've indicated. The working directory and staging index will 
			still contain all state from the last revisited commit in the project.

		* --mixed (default) is going to change the staging index to match the repository at the point in the commit we specified 
			in the command. It does not change working directory though. We could simply stage new changes and commit to repo to 
			continue with the workflow.

			<>	git reset --mixed <commit> if refers to exactly the previous commit, will behave just as if we were unstaging a file change
					from the staging index using git reset HEAD <fileName>
			<>	The staging index would be empty after this command.

		* --hard is the most destructive of all. It changes staging index and working directory to match repository.
			All changes made past the point of the commit we checkout back will be completly gone.

	*** Removing Untracked Files ***

		->When we have files that are untracked and we just want to remove them from the directory, we can use the "git clean" command
			using the -f (that stands for force) flag. This will removed any unstaged files from the working directory permanently.
			We can use the -n flag to see which files are going to be removed by the command (this represents some sort of test about 
			what the command will end up performing).

				git clean -f

### CHAPTER 08 - Ignoring Files ###

	*** Using .gitignore files ***

		->A file named .gitignore, which has to be placed at the root of the project folder, contains all the rules to indicate Git 
			which files track on our working directory and which ones ignore. The set of rules can be very simple; we could specify a
			file name on individual lines of this file and Git will ignore it appropiately; we can also provide some basic regular 
			expressions that Git will use to match file names to ignore. 

				<> We can use *, ?, [aeiou] or [0-9] as very basic regular expressionss.
				<> Negate expressions with !:

						*.php
						!index.php

				<> Ignore all files in a directory with trailing slash:

						assets/videos/

				<> Comment lines begin with #, blank lines are skipped.

		->We want to add the .gitignore file to our repository in order to allow other developers know 
			which files are getting ignore by git.

				* Example of a .gitignore file:

					# Comment
					tempfile.text
					.DS_Store
					*.zip
					*.gz
					log/*.log
					log/*.log.[0-9]
					assets/photoshop/
					assets/videos/
					!assets/videos/tour_*.mp4

					# log/archive/access.log would not be ignored for example

	*** Understanding What to Ignore ***

		*	Compiled source code.
		* Packages and compressed files.
		*	Logs and databases.
		*	Operating system generated files.
		* User-uploaded assets (images, PDFs, videos).

	*** Ignoring Files Globally ***

		* Ignore files in all repositories.
		* Settings not tracked in repository.
		* User-specific instead of repository-specific.

			git config --global core.excludesfile <DirPath>/<fileName>

				* An example name for the globally-ignored files file could be .gitignore_global

		* We can check Git's global configurations through opening .gitconfig file that it is usually 
			located in the User's home directory.

	*** Ignoring Tracked Files ***

		->A file already tracked and commited to a repository will be tracked on further changes even after we
			add it to the .gitignore file. In order to tell Git to ignore an already tracked file, we could follow
			one of the two following approaches:

				* Remove the file through "git rm <fileName>", a process that will erase the file completely from the working directory 
					and our machine as well.
				* Run the "git rm --cached <fileName>". Notice here the usage of the --cached flag, which removes the file from the 
					staging index (implicit staging index (?)). The file will still be on the working and the repository directory after
					executing the command. This change to the file is going to be reflected in the staging area for us to commit it.

	*** Tracking Empty Directories ***

		->Git is designed to be a file-tracking system. It track files and the directories it take to get to files.
			Git ignores directories with no files in it.

		->If an empty directory is desired to be kept, we could just create an empty file inside of it. A common name for this file is
			.gitkeep.
			 
### 09. Navigating the Commit Tree ###

	*** Referencing Commits ***

		->To reference commits in Git we first need to introduce a new concept called tree-ish.

				*	A tree in Git is a structure of files in the repository. It is similar to a directory in the file system.
				*	In Git, tree-ish means something that references part of the tree. It is "ish" because what that something
					means is very widely. The suffix "ish" indicates that it's like something but maybe in a vague way.
				* In its simplest term, a tree-ish refers to a commit, which in turn references the tree (the Git repo and all 
					the files that are in there at that point).

						<> Full SHA-1 hash.
						<> Short SHA-1 hash:

								- at least 4 characters.
								- unambiguous (8-10 characters).

						<> HEAD pointer.
						<> Branch reference, tag reference. The branch reference points to the tip of the branch.
						<> Using one of the previously listed methods and refer to the ancestry from that point up:

								- Parent commit:
										HEAD^, acf854^, master^ (using the caret character).
										HEAD~1, HEAD~ (using the tilda character. 1 is assumed by default when no level is provided).

								- Grandparent commit:
										HEAD^^, acf87504^^, master^^
										HEAD~2

								- Great-granparent commit:
										HEAD^^^, acf87504^^^, master^^^
										HEAD~3

	*** Exploring Tree Listings *** 

		->The command "git ls-tree" lists the contents of a tree object we passed to it. This object must be a tree-ish one. 
			There are different options we can provide to the command. All these options can be further explored running "git help ls-tree".

				* "git ls-tree HEAD" will point to the current commits contents. We could navigate further up in this tree by using 
					the caret (^) or the tilda (~) characters after the tree-ish name.

						- "git ls-tree master^ assets/" here we are exploring the current master branch's parent commit, specifically the
							contents of the "assets" directory.
						- We can also refer to tree-ish objects by using a commit SHA-1 key:

								git ls-tree 6fa98b8493af8

	*** Getting More From the Commit Log *** 

		* git log --oneline

		* git log --oneline -3: shows the last three commits from the log with sumarized info in one line per commit.
		
		* git log --since="2012-06-20": we could use "--after" instead of "--since". They are synonyms.
		
		* git log --until="2 weeks ago"
		
		*	git log --author="Oscar"
		
		*	git log --grep="temp": allows us to retrieve all related to the text temp.
		
		* git log 2907d12..acf8750 --oneline: retrieving logs by commit by range inside the specified SHA-1 keys. The first
			SHA-1 not inclusive.
		
		* git log c4b913e.. index.html: will look for all logs related to changes to index.html file starting from the specified
			commit until the last one.

		* git log -p: p stands for patch and will provide more detailed information about the logs.
		
		* git log --stat --summary: we can use these separately too. Give us an idea of the amount of lines changed and additional
			similar information.
		
		* git log --format=[oneline][full][short][medium][email][raw]
		
		* git log --graph: this shows us a graph with all of the commits in our repo. Useful when dealing with multiple branches
			git log --oneline --graph --all --decorate

	*** Viewing Commits ***

		->The command "git show [options] <object>" shows one or more objects (blobs, trees, tags and commits). 

				*	For commits it shows the log message and textual diff. It also presents the merge commit in a special format as 
					produced by git diff-tree --cc (?)

				* For trees, it shows the names (equivalent to git ls-tree with --name-only).

				* For plain blobs, it show the plain contents.

				* The command takes options applicable to the git diff-tree command to control how the changes the commit introduces
					are shown.

					<>	Usage examples:

							- git show --format=oneline HEAD
							- git show a29fd6c (commit SHA-1)

	*** Comparing Commits ***

		->When we say compare commits we are referring to the comparison of the actual directories the compared commits references.
			To be more specific, the actual state of the repositories at that given moment.	

				* A commit is not just a snapshot of the changes recently made, but it includes all of the ancestors all the way back to beginning
					of the repository as well. The sum total of all those ancestors is the directory, or tree, at that point in time where the
					commit is.
				* When we compare commits we are actually comparing two directories and seeing what could have change between them. 

		->Some examples of using the command to compare git objects:

				* git diff: compares the working directory with what it is in the staging area.

				*	git diff --staged [--cached is synonymous]: compares the staging directory with the repository at the given moment in time.

				* git diff <commit>: differences between the repo and the working directory at the given moment in time.

				* git diff <commit> <fileName>: compares a file from the specified commit with the same file in the working directory.

				*	git diff <commit>..<commit> [fileName]: compares repositories in the range specified by the given commits. Changes are filtered down to a 
					specific file if one is given in the command.

						- git diff cdae0ed..HEAD

				*	git diff --stat --summary 1506576..HEAD: gives a summary of whats changed, a list of the files, things that were added, removed, etc.

				* git diff --ignore-space-change [-b is synonymous] 1506576..HEAD: ignore changes to whitespaces.

				* git diff --ignore-all-space [-w] 1506576..HEAD: ignore all changes related to spaces.

### 10. Branching ###

	*** Branching Overview ***

		->






### CHAPTER 09 -  ###
### CHAPTER 10 -  ###
### CHAPTER 11 -  ###
### CHAPTER 12 -  ###


